## Abizeyimana Victor

PRwanda ■svicky.shema@gmail.com □+250789032290 in in/victor-abizeyimana-6a710910a/ • https://victor-abz.com

#### **SUMMARY**

A problem-solving software engineer with over 6 years of experience developing financial software in a variety of industries, primarily finance and government services. I am driven to collaborate with remote and local teams all over the world to design, build, and continuously improve processes using scalable solutions. simply, I Collaborate, Design, Build, and Improve.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

## **Technical Support Consultant**

World Bank Group

February 2022 - Present

- Conducted GRM (Grievance Redress Mechanism) pilot preparation across the country and evaluated the pilot's progress through weekly reports and communication.
- Supported the task team on the customization and deployment of the GRM (Grievance Redress Mechanism) system. This includes doing regression tests, Usability tests, and providing reports.
- Collected feedback from the end-users on usability tests and piloting functionalities planned by the Task Team.
- Delivered customized training (including responsibility for training preparation and logistics) to local audiences with/without IT skills in remote areas of Rwanda. This includes the support in the development of training materials for various categories of end-user.
- Customize training materials for local audiences as necessary.

#### Software Project Manager

Ministry of Health (MUGANGA SACCO) – Global Health Corps Fellowship (Full Time)

July 2021 - Present, Rwanda

- Led the development and implementation of a new software system, including requirements gathering, project planning, resource allocation, and quality assurance.
- Preparation of IT strategy for 2022 -2024
- Formulated internal IT procedures and strategies for various IT processes, and Guides for various IT tools used in the organization
- Successful deployment of Internet web portal that features a thorough loan application process management and member KYC management.
- Proper management of IT infrastructures and making sure they are secure and safe by designing solid Cybersecurity and disaster recovery policies.
- Design, test and deploy a loan appraisal module (Loan eligibility) for the Web portal that assists in the primary evaluation of loans through the web portal.
- Deployment of internal project management software that helps in assigning tasks to various members of the team with the capability to specify the deadline and other required items.
- Management of core banking software project implementation by liaising with external vendors and setting a clear expectation
- Managed all aspects of the project, from development to delivery, and successfully delivered the project on time and within budget.

# Senior Software Developer/Team Lead Benefactors

June 2020 - February 2022, Kigali, Rwanda

- Supervised and led a team of 5 junior software engineers during the development and rollout of a robust upgrade of digital financial software applications, resulting in improved user experience and a 33% revenue increase in 6 months.
- Documented all supported systems and applications to effectively train the new and existing team members
- Wrote efficient, reliable, and easy to maintain codes, and collaborated with other developers to share knowledge and expertise.
- Troubleshot and fixed software defects, and provided support to users.
- · Acted as a mentor to junior developers, sharing knowledge and helping them to grow and develop their skills.
- Contributed to the development of company standards and best practices.

## Software Engineer

#### Andela Rwanda

#### November 2019 - April 2020, Rwanda, Nigeria, Kenya, and Uganda

- Developed a system for managing company travel. This involves travel requests, budget preparation, and approval by managers.
- Implemented a scalable solution for handling user authentication and authorization with OAuth2 and a custom JSON web token.
- Developed a microservice architecture for a new product line in Node is and React that handles all the communication with backend services.

## Software Developer & Graphic Designer

## T-Kay Investment

January 2017 - October 2019, Kigali

- I've extended solutions to various agencies, design studios and also taken on solo projects. I improved processes and provided solutions primarily in the realms of Software Development, design, Communication Materials such as Videos and graphics, and project management.
- Wrote functional and design specifications for various software products and developed prototypes as well as performed unit testing.
- Managed software development life cycle and conducted risk assessment and mitigation.
- Graphic Design for various institutions.

• Social Media management including Search Engine Optimization. This improved the companies ranking on Google and started bringing in traffic for its branch in London(Called YE Suppliers)

## Co-Founder & CTO INEPU Ltd

July 2015 - December 2020, Kigali, Rwanda

- Led a complete overhaul of the flagship SaaS Hosting product, resulting in a 25% increase in customer satisfaction and a 14% increase in sales in the first 3 months.
- · Conceptualized, designed, and developed a Learn Management System with an Integrated Lesson plan and certification.
- · Designed, Deployed, and monitored a software hosting system managing more than 5TB of traffic daily.
- Initiated and coordinated the implementation of new data security measures across the company's IT infrastructure.

## **SIGNIFICANT PROJECTS**

## Internet Banking Web Portal (MUGANGA SACCO)

Ministry of Health (MUGANGA SACCO) • July 2021 - December 2021

- MUGANGA SACCO is an initiative by the Ministry of Health (MoH) aimed to increase the retention of medical doctors and other health workers by promoting saving and extending low-interest loans to them. I helped in the implementation, supervision, and deployment of the web portal by the development team.
- The platform manages the monthly savings of each healthcare professional and features the management of Loan origination, disbursement, and collection efforts. My role involved the coordination, implementation, and supervision of the software design specifications and development. The platform is expected to manage nearly 10,000 Medical professionals with more than 5bn RWF in savings.
- Design, test and supervise the deployment of **loan appraisal module** (Loan eligibility) for the Web portal that assists in the primary evaluation of loans through the web portal before they are sent to the core banking.

## Rosling - Financial Management Software

Benefactors • July 2020 - February 2022

- In 2020, I designed and developed a robust system for benefactors, a non-deposit financial institution. The system equipped benefactors with various modules such as **loan applications management**, **Loan disbursement**, **monitoring**, **and fees calculation**. The app includes strict validation features and user validation from application approval to the amount being disbursed. It features also rich dashboards on loan performance. This software provides various reporting requirements such as **CRB reports**, **BNR Reports and other reports directed to various internal request and management**
- Development and deployment of AI robot to help track loan applicant performance on external systems such as credit bureau and public tenders (RPPA). This result in getting timely information of backlisted applicants and help in decision making
- I migrated big datasets from an old google sheet-based system to a new system without business disruption and onboard the team members to the new platform without business disruption.
- Currently, the project manages more than Rwf 5.6 million extended to various SMEs.

#### Midas Loan Dashboards - Consultancy

PesaChoice • November 2021 - January 2022

• Lead development of a feature Rich dashboard for PesaChoice, the dashboard allows them to view business metrics in real-time such as loan performance and portfolio management. The System involves predictive analytics to predict trends based on historical data which gives an early warning system to Pesa Choice. I lead a team of developers, gather requirements, and supervise the project to stays on budget and on time.

#### Loan Management System-Consultancy

PesaChoice • June 2021 - December 2021

- Designed a loan management system for PesaChoice. The system extends loans to various employees through an existing Payroll system. I lead a small team to design, deploy and maintain the system using agile methodology. Testing the product using Chai, Mocha, and Jest as well as automatic deployments using CI/CD.
- The loan software actively helps PesaChoice to streamline and automate loan origination, processing, and supervising payments.
- The software also helps to keep track of the employee loans and repayment schedules.

#### ML Based Credit Scoring- Consultancy

PesaChoice • June 2021 - December 2021

- I designed and developed an ML-based credit(loan) scoring system for PesaChoice. The ML-based system allows PesaChoice to control its risk exposure through the selective allocation of loans based on the statistical analysis of historical customer data.
- The system correctly identifies high-risk customers with a high degree of accuracy of around 89%, which helps the company to better manage its credit risk.
- The system helps the company to improve its customer service by allowing it to provide loans to more worthy customers without spending much time on analysis. The number of customers served weekly increased by more than 45% since its deployment in January 2022.

#### Virtual Sales Data Controller

Benefactors • January 2021 - February 2022

- In 2021, I lead a team of 5 developers as project managers in the design and deployment of a Virtual Sales Data Controller (VSDC) for Benefactors. The goal of this project launched an invoicing system that provides a cost-effective tool to enable SMEs to comply with tax regulations requiring EBM (Electronic Billing Machine) invoices on all sales and provide the BeneFactors team with a sales history of SMEs to prequalify them for working capital loans.
- I led the development team of developers through requirements gathering, design, development, and testing using Agile Methodology. I also ensured that we delivered on time and within budget by conducting necessary scrum ceremonies.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### **Bachelor of Business Administration**

With Hon in Finance • University of Rwanda • Rwanda

#### Math, Physics and Computer Science

ES Kanombe • Kigali, Rwanda

#### **CERTIFICATIONS**

#### Software Development

Andela • 2020

Certified in Modern software development practice

#### **Project Management**

Global Enterprise Experience • 2017

Certified in a standardized and evolving set of project management principles

#### **SKILLS**

Project Management, Agile Methodology, Human-Centered Design, Software Product Design, Test-Driven Development with Mocha/Chai, and Jest. Continuous Development (CI/CD),

Frontend: React, HTML, CSS, JavaScript

Backend: NodeJS, Python, Django

DevOps: Deployment, Server monitoring

#### **SARA OON JIAN**

Country Director Benefactors sjoon6@gmail.com +250784442231

## **UWAJENEZA Clement**

Country Director – Andela, current MD at Equip Rwanda bdushimimana@outlook.com +250782769303

#### **DAVIS NTEZIRYAYO**

CEO - PesaChoice davis.nteziryayo@pesachoice.com +250781067884

#### **NGIZWENAYO** William

Co-Founder - Inepu ngizwewilliam@gmail.com +250789723337